<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Über Dig</title><link href="http://www.levigross.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.levigross.com/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.levigross.com/</id><updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>37 Tips For Interviewing a company</title><link href="http://www.levigross.com/2014/01/01/37-tips-for-interviewing-a-company/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Levi Gross</name></author><id>tag:www.levigross.com,2014-01-01:2014/01/01/37-tips-for-interviewing-a-company/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many articles have been written about assessing interview candidates; however, I have not seen many written on how interview candidates should assess the companies and jobs they are interviewing for. I have compiled a list of things to look out for — this will (hopefully) help you avoid working at a toxic&amp;nbsp;environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a list of things that &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt; look out for when joining companies that I don&amp;#8217;t know much about. You may not agree with everything listed here. I welcome your feedback and&amp;nbsp;counterarguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the great quest for the perfect working environment, there is no &amp;#8220;one size fits all&amp;#8221; solution. This list is by no means complete, please feel free to contribute to the items listed here. I will do my best to update it, and give&amp;nbsp;credit. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first section is a list of items to avoid. Obviously, if a company does not exhibit the behaviors mentioned below, it is probably good place to&amp;nbsp;join. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to&amp;nbsp;avoid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Avoid locations that are &lt;em&gt;obsessed&lt;/em&gt; with a specific technology stack (unless you are as&amp;nbsp;well)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s face it, technology stacks are a means to an end. Focusing on the technology instead of the solution is a recipe for disaster. Specific technology stacks are not guarantees for success and therefore should not be obsessed&amp;nbsp;over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Avoid locations with excessive technical&amp;nbsp;debt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This must be balanced with what is mentioned above. If the company allows their employees &lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt; freedom in adding to the technical stack, you should steer clear. A company&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_factor"&gt;Bus Factor&lt;/a&gt; is very important. No one wants to spend a weekend learning some arcane system, because the person that maintained it has left the company and a new critical bug was just&amp;nbsp;discovered. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.  Avoid locations where the people who are conducting the interview look&amp;nbsp;overworked&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the employees look overworked, if you join you will be overworked as&amp;nbsp;well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Avoid locations that will not be able to tell you what your initial workload will look&amp;nbsp;like&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you join a company, the company should have a somewhat accurate estimate of what your initial workload should look like (at least for the first 3-6 months). Avoid places that&amp;nbsp;don&amp;#8217;t. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5.  Avoid locations that seriously affect your quality of&amp;nbsp;life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your quality of life is important, and you should be assertive in ensuring that your new job won&amp;#8217;t have a detrimental effect on it. I can &lt;strong&gt;guarantee&lt;/strong&gt; that a company doesn&amp;#8217;t care how many all nighters you pull to get the job done. All they care about is how to effectively make use of their &lt;em&gt;human capital&lt;/em&gt; and will squeeze you for all your worth. Your job requires your full mental capacity, which requires that you maintain a certain quality of&amp;nbsp;life. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6.  If you are offered a higher salary in exchange for less equity, take the higher&amp;nbsp;salary.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equity rarely amounts to anything significant. Many times it is used to pacify overworked employees. Take the extra cash today. This only applies if you cannot sell the equity on an&amp;nbsp;exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;7. Avoid locations that do not have an official ramp-up&amp;nbsp;process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every employee, no matter how senior, must learn how things work at every company they join. Your initial days will require a lot of &amp;#8220;hand holding&amp;#8221; and help. This is normal. Avoid places that throw you into the lion&amp;#8217;s den with a dull&amp;nbsp;knife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;8. Avoid locations that have even &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=brogrammer"&gt;brogrammer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, even &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; bad employee can ruin the environment for&amp;nbsp;everyone. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9. Avoid locations with immature and childish&amp;nbsp;employees&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to work in a place where people are respectful and mature. Otherwise, office drama will play a serious part of your work&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;10. Avoid locations with conceited&amp;nbsp;people&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one wants to be around conceited people, let alone work with&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;11. Avoid locations that shun&amp;nbsp;diversity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to work at places that embrace diversity. Remember, the reason the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt; is one of the most welcoming places on earth, is that we embrace&amp;nbsp;diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;12. Avoid places that don&amp;#8217;t respect you or your&amp;nbsp;property&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be interpreted in many ways and I will leave this up to the reader&amp;#8217;s intuition. However, I will provide one example. If your company expects you to use your cellphone as a part of your job, they should at least pay &lt;strong&gt;some&lt;/strong&gt; if not your entire cellphone bill (in addition to your current salary) or provide you with a company&amp;nbsp;cellphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;13. Avoid locations that lack a systematic&amp;nbsp;processes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Processes and policies allow companies to scale. A lack of some form of standardization will lead to all sorts of technical and logistical&amp;nbsp;debt. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;14. Avoid locations with no office&amp;nbsp;culture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every company, big and small should have some form of office culture. You want to work in a friendly environment and be on good terms with your co-workers. Many of these relationships can be fostered at company events.  A company that lacks culture, lacks&amp;nbsp;harmony. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;15. Avoid locations that have unwelcome surprises during the&amp;nbsp;interview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you experience an unwelcome surprise during the interview, imagine how many &amp;#8220;surprises&amp;#8221; you will experience during your&amp;nbsp;employment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;16. Avoid locations that ask useless interview&amp;nbsp;questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are asked questions that are not relevant to the job you are interviewing for, decline to answer them. Here is an example of a useless interview&amp;nbsp;question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many traffic lights are there in New York&amp;nbsp;City?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;17. Avoid locations that ask you to contribute to their code base during the interview&amp;nbsp;process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are being interviewed and have not been hired. You should not be working on the company&amp;#8217;s code base during your&amp;nbsp;interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;18. Avoid locations that ask you to take a large amount of time off of work to interview without compensating&amp;nbsp;you&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company should respect the time that the interview candidates takes to come in to interview. If they ask you to take a day or two off to interview, it should compensate you &lt;strong&gt;monetarily&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;19. Avoid locations that do not have a code of&amp;nbsp;ethics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A code of ethics is very important and every company should possess one. Avoid places that&amp;nbsp;don&amp;#8217;t. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;20. Avoid locations with an unlimited paid vacation&amp;nbsp;policy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a nice way of saying &amp;#8220;The company vacation &lt;em&gt;policy&lt;/em&gt; is subject to our discretion on a case by case basis&amp;#8221;. Knowing how much paid vacation you are entitled to allows you to plan your vacation and not have to worry if you&amp;#8217;re asking for too&amp;nbsp;much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;21. Avoid locations with questionable business&amp;nbsp;practices&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the company you are interviewing by may be breaking the law or doing something &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; deem unethical, walk&amp;nbsp;away. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;22. Avoid locations with individual ownership&amp;nbsp;requirements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All new and current systems should be owned by the engineering team. You don&amp;#8217;t want to be the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; one on call for everything &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; build. It leads to a culture where people are afraid to innovate in fear of losing their nights and&amp;nbsp;weekends. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;23. Avoid locations that &lt;em&gt;force&lt;/em&gt; you to use your &lt;em&gt;personal&lt;/em&gt; social media accounts for company&amp;nbsp;advertisements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is fine for a company to &lt;em&gt;ask&lt;/em&gt; you to post company announcements or job listings on your social media accounts. It is not &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt; for them to force&amp;nbsp;you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;24. Avoid locations with a high turn over&amp;nbsp;rate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a company cannot retain employees, there is a good reason for&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;25. Avoid locations that are not a&amp;nbsp;meritocracy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a company doesn&amp;#8217;t show appreciation for the hard work their employees put in, it doesn&amp;#8217;t deserve the employees working for them and you shouldn&amp;#8217;t join. And no, mugs and tee-shirts aren&amp;#8217;t considered merit based monetary raises and&amp;nbsp;bonuses!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Questions to ask during your&amp;nbsp;interview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;26. Obtain very specific information about the company&amp;#8217;s employee benefits&amp;nbsp;package&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many companies offer benefit packages. Make sure you get a very clear picture of what is included, in particular: health, dental and vision benefits. A better benefits package can sometimes trump a higher salary. Here is an incomplete list of questions you should ask about a company&amp;#8217;s benefit&amp;nbsp;package:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which insurance company provides the medical, dental, vision&amp;nbsp;plans?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the plan&amp;nbsp;names?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you please send me a copy of the medical, dental, and vision&amp;nbsp;plans?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you please send me a complete list of all of the benefits&amp;nbsp;provided?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long after joining the company do the medical, dental, and vision&amp;nbsp;begin?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are there any limits or caveats that I should know&amp;nbsp;about?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;27. Obtain very specific information about the companies tech&amp;nbsp;stack&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reverse interview the employees about the work they do and the technology they use. Feel free to ask them about every detail, no matter how insignificant it may seem. This will show you at least 3&amp;nbsp;things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well the current employees understand the stack that they are&amp;nbsp;using. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The technical debt that you will be dealing with (should you decide to&amp;nbsp;join).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If they make sane technical&amp;nbsp;decisions. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;28. Ask the employees to tell you something they don&amp;#8217;t like about their current&amp;nbsp;job&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is very important. Familiarity breeds contempt, and how employees answer this question will tell you a lot about the&amp;nbsp;company. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;29. Look at &lt;a href="http://www.glassdoor.com/"&gt;GlassDoor.com&lt;/a&gt; before you go in for an&amp;nbsp;interview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GlassDoor.com can give you some insight into company internals; make use of&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;30. Reach out to former employees and ask them about their&amp;nbsp;experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be polite and don&amp;#8217;t be pushy. Let them know you are considering joining company &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XYZ&lt;/span&gt; and you would like to hear about their experiences at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XYZ&lt;/span&gt;  company. Their insight can provide invaluable information on whether or not you should join &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XYZ&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;company. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;31. Identify a list of reasons you would like to join the company and validate those&amp;nbsp;reasons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say you want to join &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XYZ&lt;/span&gt; Inc because they use Python. During the interview ask how and when they use Python. Ensure that the company&amp;#8217;s use of Python is what you are looking for. Knowing what you are getting into is very&amp;nbsp;important. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;32. If the company has public code on GitHub, look it&amp;nbsp;over&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every company has their own engineering process. When a company publishes code, they are usually proud of it. This is one of the best ways to gauge the engineering process within a&amp;nbsp;company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;33. Find something technical to criticize and &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;politely&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt; mention it during the&amp;nbsp;interview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dealing with criticism is an important part of every job, especially technical jobs. Being mature when accepting both valid and invalid criticism is very&amp;nbsp;important. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, you should gauge the response. If you don&amp;#8217;t like the response or the way that they deal with the critique, walk&amp;nbsp;away. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;34. If you interview with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CEO&lt;/span&gt; of the company, question as if you were looking to invest in the&amp;nbsp;company&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you work for a company, you&amp;#8217;re throwing your lot with the company&amp;#8217;s lot. Make sure the company is making sound business decisions. Here is an incomplete list of questions you should ask the company&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CEO&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you feel are the biggest challenges the business will face within the next 6&amp;nbsp;months?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your plan to overcome those&amp;nbsp;challenges?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What were the biggest challenges that the business overcame in the past 6&amp;nbsp;months?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;35. Speak with the employees of the company at&amp;nbsp;meetups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may learn things that are not mentioned during the interview and/or you may meet an employee whom you did not interview with. This can also help you gain insight into other parts of the&amp;nbsp;company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;36. Try to understand the company&amp;#8217;s recent&amp;nbsp;history&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the company just underwent some big changes, find out what was changed, why it was changed, how it was changed, and what the desired effect was on the company or team&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;process/performance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;37. Obtain a clear list of expectations for the job that you are interviewing&amp;nbsp;for&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gauge whether you feel that expectations are excessive. It will also help you negotiate a higher salary should they be&amp;nbsp;excessive. &lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Welcome to My new Blog</title><link href="http://www.levigross.com/2014/01/01/welcome-to-my-new-blog/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Levi Gross</name></author><id>tag:www.levigross.com,2014-01-01:2014/01/01/welcome-to-my-new-blog/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Welcome to the new version of&amp;nbsp;LeviGross.com&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have decided to move off of tumblr (because no one likes fighting with their blog to display content). I am going to move everything from Tumblr within the next few days (hopefully), so please be&amp;nbsp;patient.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>